<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="ChristmasPlay/Christmas-Play.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<ChristmasPlay>
<Title>CHRISTMAS BELLS</Title>
<Description>A One Act Play for Children</Description>
by
<Author>ANNA J. COOPER</Author>
<DramaticPersons>DRAMATIS PERSONAE</DramaticPersons>
<ListPerson type = "index"><Character>HANNAH</Character>, aged eleven, “the little Mother,” who has the
care of her two sisters, while the Mother works by the
day, away from home. The Father is a soldier, across
the sea.
<Person age="8">NANNETTE</Person>, aged eight
<Person age="4">ANNIKINS</Person>, aged four
THE THREE KINGS,—
<Person>Gaspard</Person>, a European,
<Person>Melchior</Person>, an Asiatic,
<Person>Balthazar</Person>, an African.
<Choir type="Angels">Chorus of Angels</Choir>
<Choir type="Shepherd">Chorus of Shepherd</Choir>s
Sunshine Club of the Community Service. Soldiers. Red
Cross Nurses</ListPerson>
<SceneHeading>SCENE I</SceneHeading>
Before the curtain rises, Christinas chimes arc heard,
playing distinctly,—“Christians, awake! Salute the happy morn, Whereon the Savior of mankind was born!*
A t the close of the chimes a pause of jo seconds absolute silence; after which there sounds shrill and clear a
single stroke of a bell. The curtain rises, disclosing a
room of a humble family of three children. “ The little
Mother" is busy about the evening meal; Nannette is
setting the table; Annikins, on the floor, cuts pictures
for paper dolls.
<SPEAKER sex="f">NANNETTE</SPEAKER>. What are the bells ringing for?
<SPEAKER sex="f">HANNAH</SPEAKER>. Why, don’t you know dear? They're ringing
for the Christmas Child—for His birthday. This is Christmas Eve!
<SPEAKER>ANNIKINS</SPEAKER>. Is Christ Child coming here?
<SPEAKER>HANNAH</SPEAKER>. (Thoughtfully) Why yes, Annikins. He will
come to us if we try to be kind and good.
<SPEAKER>NANNETTE</SPEAKER>. Sister, can’t we possibly have a Christmas
tree this year ?
<SPEAKER>HANNAH</SPEAKER>. I’m afraid not, deary. But we’ll try to be happy
just the same. We’ll play “make believe’’ and make each
other wonderful presents. It's lots of fun! And write
letters to Daddy, and we’ll ask the Christ Child to bring
Daddy safe home to us, and then mother will not have to
work so hard down town. And we’ll ask the Christ Child
to bring us sweet Peace and Good Will. Because lie is the
Prince of Peace, and that’s what He is coming for. And
then I s'pose we ought to pray for Democracy, ’cause
that’s what Daddy is fighting for.
<SPEAKER>NANNETTE</SPEAKER>. What is Democracy?
<SPEAKER>HANNAH</SPEAKER>. I’m not sure I know, little sister. It’s kind of
hard to understand. But it must be what the Christ Child
wants every where in the world—for it means every body
will be good and kind to every body and there'll not be
any poor people who can’t get enough to eat, nor any unkind people who scorn and hate. Just all the world will
love each other like you and I and Annikins love one
another. Every body will be helping to make the world
good and pleasant for every body else and so the Christ
Child will come back to us again and He will be our Big
Brother and all the people will be brothers ’cause you see
they will all be His brothers. Come now Annikins, put
away your paper dollies. Supper is ready.
(She smoothes the child's hair, examines hands and face
to see that they arc clean, and lifts her into a high-chair
at the table. The others take their places and, with
bowed heads and folded hands, sing the grace) —
God is great and God is good,
And we thank thee for this food;
By thy hand must we be fed,
Give us, Lord, our daily bread. Amen.
ANNIKINS. Pass the sugar! (correcting herself) Excuse
me sister, please pass the sugar!
HANNAH. Oo-h Annikins! [Don't take quite so much, love!
Uncle Sam says we can't have any more sugar till next
month!
ANNIKINS. (Confidentially to her big sister) you tell the
Christmas Child / want some sugar,—hear? (Carol singers
are heard outside)
HANNAH. Hush, child, listen. It’s the carol singers!
CAROL SINGERS.
Christmas where children are hopeful and gay,
Christmas where old men are patient and gray,
Christmas with peace, like a dove in its flight,
Over brave men in the thick of the fight.
Everywhere, everywhere, Christmas tonight!
Immediately after the carols the Sunshine Club come
bursting in, covered with snow. The boys tc-car muffllers.
Some have ice-skates hung over their shoulders. Two
of the boys lug in a tree all ready to set up. The girls
have their arms full of trinkets for the tree and presents
for the children. They are bubbling over with spirits
and gayly shouting,—“Merry Christmas Hannah! Merry Christmas Nanncttc! Hello, Annikins! Merry
Christmas!" Their leader gives the child a bear-hug,
and presents her with a wonderful doll, almost as big
as the four-year-old herself. Nan net te gets a beautiful
red dress and a string of beads. The children clap their
hands in glee. While dressing the tree they sing.
There’s a wonderful tree a wonderful tree
The happy children rejoice to see.
Spreading its branches year by year
It comes from the forest to flourish here.
Oh this beautiful tree with its branches wide
Is always blooming at Christmas T ide;
And a voice is telling its boughs among
Of the Shepherds’ watch and the Angels’ song;
Of a holv Babe in the manger low—
The beautiful story of long ago—
When a radiant star threw its beams so wide
To herald the earliest Christmas Tide.
(Joining hands, and singing, they dance around the
tree)
4
<Person>HANNAH</Person>. <paraenthetical>(A little shyly at first)</paraenthetical> Oh thank you! Thank
you so much girls. What a beautiful tree! Oh, we are
so happy—I had no idea we would have a tree!
1st SUNSHINE GIRL. (Hanging a small doll on the tree)
Here is a baby-doll for Annikins; skates for Xannette.
And here, little Mother, is a gay peasant-kerchief and a
picture storybook for you. I know you’ll read the stories
to the rest. Hannah never keeps anything all for herself!
<Person>HANNAH</Person>. <paraenthetical>(Somewhat embarrassed)</paraenthetical> Oh girls, I—I can’t
tell you how much—Oh, I mean you are so good and
kind—I just don’t know how to thank you.
1st SUNSHINE GIRL. Oh don’t thank us at all, just thank
the Christ Child!
2nd SUNSHINE GIRL. All who love the Christ Child are
trying to make little children happy tonight, don't you
know? We don’t want a single child to be forgotten. His
love will warm and cheer the loneliest child on earth.
HANNAH. <paraenthetical>(Thoughtfully)</paraenthetical> Yes. All for the Christ Child
who was born tonight. To love Him is to love all little
children.
<Group type="girls">SUNSHINE GIRLS</Group>. <paraenthetical>(Putting on their wraps, waving Merry Christmas to all; shaking hands affectionately with
Hannah)</paraenthetical>. Good night everybody! Be good children!
Good night,—good night!
<Group type="all">THE CHILDREN</Group>. Good night! Merry Christmas!
ANNIKINS. <paraenthetical>(Piping up)</paraenthetical> <language type="French">Au revoir-au revoir!</language> <paraenthetical>(Exit S.S.
Club laughing and throwing kisses. A pause)</paraenthetical>
NANXETTE. What a wonderful tree! <paraenthetical>(They examine the
presents)</paraenthetical>
</ChristmasPlay>
